Guide to the Orrin Leslie Elliott Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Orrin Leslie Elliott papers
1860-1940
1891-1936
SC0007
Elliott, Orrin Leslie, 1860-1940
3 Linear feet (9 boxes)
This collection consists of notes, source citations, unpublished reminiscences, and copies of documents collected for, and the original manuscript of, Elliott's STANFORD UNIVERSITY; THE FIRST TWENTY-FIVE YEARS (1937). Also includes correspondence of George Crothers and notecards for Crother's FOUNDING OF THE LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY (1932).
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
This collection was given to Stanford University by O. L. Elliott.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Orrin Leslie Elliott was an English instructor at Cornell University and first registrar of Stanford University (1891-1925; emeritus 1925-1940).
Description of the Collection
This collection consists of notes, source citations, unpublished reminiscences, and copies of documents collected for, and the original manuscript of Elliott's STANFORD UNIVERSITY; THE FIRST TWENTY-FIVE YEARS (1937). Also includes correspondence of George Crothers and notecards for Crother's FOUNDING OF THE LELAND STANFORD JUNIOR UNIVERSITY (1932).
Access Terms
Branner, John Casper, 1850-1922.; Coolidge, Charles Allerton, 1858-1936.; Crothers, George E. (George Edward), 1870-1957.; Elliott, Orrin Leslie, 1860-1940; Jordan, David Starr, 1851-1931; Jordan, Jessie Knight, 1867?-1952; Lathrop, Ariel; Nash, Herbert C.; Newton, Heber.; Olmsted, Frederick Law, 1822-1903; Peterson, Harry C.; Ross, Edward Alsworth, 1866-1951.; Stanford, Jane Lathrop, 1828-1905.; Veblen, Thorstein, (Thorstein Bunde), 1857-1929.; Axe, Stanford--Recaptured.; Manuscripts (for publication).; San Francisco Earthquake and Fire, Calif., 1906; Students, Foreign.; Sunday--Tuesday lectures.; The Camp.; Training House.; Universities and colleges--Accreditation.; Universities and colleges--Buildings.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Death of Mrs. Stanford (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous personal clippings (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Original manuscript: Stanford University, A History, Part I: Founding a University (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Original manuscript: Stanford University, A History, Part 2: Progress of events, the University (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Original manuscript: Stanford University, A History, Part 2: Progress of events, student affairs and doings (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Original manuscript: Stanford University, A History, Part 3: Problems of Administration, #1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Original manuscript: Stanford University, A History, Part 3: Problems of administration, #2 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Original manuscript: Stanford University, A History, Part 3: Problems of administration, #3 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Original manuscript: Stanford University, A History, Part 4: Trustees and the University (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Original manuscript: Stanford University, A History: Preface and epilogue (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Original manuscript: Stanford University, A History: Appendix (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Replies to Pres. Jordan' s circular regarding the responsibility for graduate degrees (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Articles of organization of the faculty, interpretation and revision (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Extracts from Exec. Committee minutes, 1911; Interpretation of articles of organization adopted by Exec. Committee, 1911; Academic Council mintues, 1/12/12; a few letters.
  - Heber Newton Correspondence (copies) (Box 2, Folder 2)
    OLE' s copies of 18 letters regarding Heber Newton' s resignation.
  - Pioneer Class (Box 2, Folder 3)
    OLE' s statistics
  - Nash manuscript (The Train Robber) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Mrs. Branner' s early days at Stanford (Box 2, Folder 5)
    OLE' s copy, 9 pages
  - Mrs. Jordan on Mrs. Stanford, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    OLE' s copy of Mrs. Jordan' s paper read before the P.A. chapter of the DAR
  - Univ. of California re cooperation with Stanford on accreditation, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    OLE' s copies of two Martin Kellogg letters to DSJ, 11/14/91 and 12/10/91, and one copy of a letter to DSJ from the sec' y of the U.C. Academic Council, 12/10/91
  - Criticism of Stanford, circa 1930-1931 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Four articles critical of Hoover' s influence at S.U. and Wilbur' s absence
  - Miss Berner' s reminiscences (copy of letter), 1915 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    Newspaper copy of letter from Berner to Mrs. P. Treat re Mrs. Stanford
  - Jane Stanford Lathrop Watson to Mr. Clark, 1932 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - The camp by the Coolidges, circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Typed accounts by several Coolidges
  - Frederick Law Olmsted to Leland Stanford (copy), August 7, 1890 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    OLE' s copy of letter re dealings with Ariel Lathrop
  - Stanfords at Harvard and Cornell, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    OLE' s copies of letters re the Stanfords' visit to Harvard and Cornell: C.W. Eliot to DSJ and DSJ to Andrew White
  - First life insurance policy (copy) (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Copy of $10,000 policy cashed after Mr. Stanford' s death
  - Dr. Jordan' s 60th birthday, speech by Prof. M.B. Anderson, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    OLE' s copy
  - Earthquake proclamation and clippings, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Proclamation 6/12/06 announcing August opening; and 3 newspaper clippings
  - Axe recaptured, clippings (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - H. C. Peterson correspondence, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Two letters of recollection to OLE
  - John F. Sheehan re tax exemption amendment campaign, circa 1899 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    OLE' s copy of Sheehan to DSJ, 8/27/99 (?)
  - Ross affair; correspondence with O.L. Elliott (Box 2, Folder 20)
    Public opinion and reaction
  - Ross affair; clippings and documents collected by O.L. Elliott (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Ross affair; Edward T. Maples statement, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    Two letters
  - Coolidge and Walker letters re University's architecture, 1932-1936 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Charles Coolidge to OLE, 1932; letters by Francis Walker, 1932, re Gen. Walker; Emory Smith to OLE, 1932-36
  - Conversations with George E. Crothers, 1931-1932 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    OLE' s copy of George Crothers longhand recollections
  - Training house, 1901-1902 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Two letters; copies of description in 1901 and 1902 Quad
  - Academic robes, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Copy of a letter from E. Rosencrantz, 1936
  - Misc. manuscripts pertaining to O.L. Elliott and Stanford University, 1891-1898 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    A. Candidates for professorships B. Roll books, economics, 1891-92 C. Sunday - Tuesday lectures, 1894-95 D. Elliott' s guide to printing orders, 1897-98 E. Receipt book for student loans [?], 1897
  - Misc. notes by Elliott; Letters by Archie Rice and Yamato Ichihashi (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Misc. notes by OLE: Archie Rice to Mrs. Jordan (copy) re box car incident and theft of wine for Pres. Harrison: T. Kinney (?) to OLE, Feb. 27, 1903, re academic performance of Japanese students at SU: Yamato Ichihashi to OLE, Oct. 12, 1907, re academic credits for work done in Japanese colleges; and June 6, 1910, re Japanese colleges
  - George E. Crother's "outline history" of the founding of Leland Stanford Junior University (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Four printed copies, one annotated
  - George E. Crothers correspondence; article on coeducation at Stanford, Nov. 4, 1929 - Oct. 28, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - George E. Crothers correspondence, Nov. 17, 1931 - Sept. 1932 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - George E. Crothers correspondence, Aug. 28, 1933 - Oct. 2, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - George E. Crothers, educational ideals of Jane L. Stanford (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - George E. Crothers, rules for conduct of women students (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - George E. Crothers, the government suit (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - George E. Crothers, last letter from Mrs. Stanford (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Biographical sketch of George E. Crothers (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous clippings and articles (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous clippings and articles (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous clippings and articles (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Stanford history notes, A-F (Box 4)
  - Stanford history notes, G-N (Box 5)
  - Stanford history notes, O-R (Box 6)
  - Stanford history notes, S-Students (Hazing) (Box 7)
  - Stanford history notes, Students (Liquor)-Y (Box 8)
  - Bound volume: Elliott's copies of memoranda of actions approved by Leland Stanford, March 1891 to May 1893; and faculty salaries for 1893-94 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Loose items from bound volume (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Two approvals by Leland Stanford, 1892-1893; and note by David Starr Jordan